Guide to the General John Sedgwick Papers 1776-1994 (Bulk 1776-1950) MS 034 MS 034 MS 034
Cornwall Historical Society
General John Sedgwick Papers
1776-1994
, (Bulk 1776-1950)
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 034
3 linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains items related to Union Army general and Cornwall native, John Sedgwick (1813-1864).
Provenance
The collection was begun through the collections of town historian E.C. Starr, but was expanded and organized by subsequent historians and presidents of the Cornwall Historical Society, such as Emily E. Marsh and Michael Gannett.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Sedgwick (1813-1864) was born in Cornwall Hollow on September 13, 1813 to one of the community’s most prominent families. He taught school in his hometown for two winters before entering the United States Military Academy at West Point, where he graduated in 1837. Prior to the Civil War, Sedgwick fought as an artillery officer in the Seminole War, took part in the removal of the Cherokee from Georgia, and served first as a captain, and later as a major, in the Mexican-American War. Following the Mexican-American War, Sedgwick served for several years in Western United States, first in Utah and later in Kansas. By 1860, his personal correspondence reveals that Sedgwick was ready to retire from military life and return to Cornwall; the start of the Civil War put a stop to those plans.
At the beginning of the war, Sedgwick held the rank of colonel, and served with distinction in the Eastern Theater, resulting in a promotion to the rank of general. In 1862 at the Battle of Antietam, Sedgwick had two horses shot from under him, and received three wounds. After being carried off of the battlefield, Sedgwick returned to Cornwall to convalesce in his recently-completed new home. After a brief recovery period, Sedgwick returned to the Eastern Theater, and fought at the battles of Chancellorsville and Gettysburg. On May 9, 1864, at Spotsylvania, Virginia, after his troops came under fire from a sharpshooter, Sedgwick refused to take cover and chided his men for their fear of marksmen so far away; Sedgwick was then shot under the left eye and killed instantly. His body was transported home and laid to rest in the Cornwall Hollow Cemetery.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains six archival boxes of material. The first three boxes contain the personal papers of General John Sedgwick and are organized into categories devoted to his military service and correspondence. The fourth box contains items related to Sedgwick’s family, while the final two containers hold information concerning memorials to General Sedgwick.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically by subject then chronologically within each subject.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Official Documents
Correspondence
Family Papers
Tributes and Memorials
Miscellaneous Materials
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; military records; Articles; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Sedgwick, John, 1813-1864
- Official Documents
  - Mexican-American War
    - General Orders No. 284, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Proceedings regarding amnesty for the officers of the 1st Division of Regulars and their commanders, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes regarding design ideas for commemorative ring for veterans, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - State of Conn. Commendation, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Plains Wars
    - Order from Secretary of War Jefferson Davis for deployment to Kansas, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Special Orders relating to military operations in Kansas and Utah, 1857-1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Treasury Department balance sheets, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Request for military protection at Kansas election, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Civil War
    - Invitation to US House of Representatives session, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Telegraph from US Army Chief of Staff, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letter sent from Adjunct General Hillhouse, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reports of division engagements, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letter from the War Department, regarding arrest of Anthony Dwyer, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Map of Peninsular Campaign, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Confidential information on the strength of the Army of Northern Virginia, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Photozincographic map of Confederate troops at Fredericksburg, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Communication regarding General Orders No. 101, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter from the War Department, regarding service record, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Newspaper clipping and letter of exoneration, regarding Chancellorsville Campaign, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Telegraph regarding foraging, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - State commendation, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter from General George McClellan, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Photograph of horse, possibly Handsome Dan, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Copy of General Orders No. 67, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - General Orders Collection, 1854-1861 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Recommended change to Army Manual, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Military Receipts
    - Military receipts, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Military receipts, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Military receipts, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Military receipts, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Military receipts, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Military receipts, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Military receipts, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Military receipts, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Military receipts, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Military receipts, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Military receipts, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Military receipts, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence
    - Correspondence with father, Benjamin Sedgwick, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with cousin, G.M. Sedgwick, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with nephew Sedgwick Pratt, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with sister, Emily Sedgwick Welch, 1857-1861 (Box 3, Folder 4-8)
    - Correspondence with niece, Maria, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Friend Correspondence
    - Letter from B. Clark, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with A. Gibson, 1859-1862 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letter from Chas. G. Merchant, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Military Correspondence
    - Correspondence with "Bayard", 1859 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with S.D. Baylor, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Letter sent by W. Beall, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Letter from William F. Berry, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Letter from H. Clarke, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with "Colbunn", 1859 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Letter from M.O. Davidson, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Letter from Matilda W. Emory, regarding William R. Emory, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence with W.H. French, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Telegraphs from Brigadier General Gregg, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Letter from J.E. Johnston, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence with W.A. Nichols, 1859-1862 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Letter from H. Prince, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Letter from Harriet Fanning Read, US Gen. Hospital worker, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Letter from F. Schack, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Invitation from Major General Scott, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Sealed return of ordinance written by John Sedgwick, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Letter with promotion to Major General from Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Letter from E. Tanner, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Letter from A.P. Taylor, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence with Randal Whittier, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Empty envelopes addressed to John Sedgwick, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Letter to Brigadier General S. Williams from Major General E. Sumner, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Family Papers
  - Gen. John Sedgwick Ancestors
    - Writings of grandfather, Judge John Sedgwick, 1783-1815 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Transcribed letter from Theodore Sedgwick to Truman Sedgwick, 1776 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gen. John Sedgwick Siblings and Cousins
    - Account of the life of sister, Eliza Sedgwick (1824-1831), by Olive Sedgwick Fuller, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence between cousin Hon. John Sedgwick of New York and E.C. Starr, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Sister, Emily Sedgwick Welch correspondence with Captain R.T. Halsted, 1863-1866 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Emily Sedgwick Welch correspondence with General Whittier, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Emily Sedgwick Welch correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1892-1897; , undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Emily Sedgwick Welch correspondence regarding biography published about Gen. John Sedgwick, 1899-1900 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sedgwick Descendants
    - Letter sent from Alden Bryan Sedgwick to "Uncle Charles", 1922 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Charles F. Sedgwick writings, 1870-1899 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Harry Sedgwick correspondence and writings, 1899-1905 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - E.C. Starr’s notes on Sedgwick family, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Tributes and memorials
  - Memorial Letters
    - Fragment of memorial letter from Gen. John M. Wilson, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Cornwall city clerk from veteran John C. Johnston, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cornwall Memorials
    - Funeral program, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Memorial Day Exercises pamphlets, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper account of Memorial Day Exercises, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - E.C. Starr correspondence regarding Cornwall Hollow Memorial, 1893-1897 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence between E.C. Starr and T.S. Gold regarding placement of a bronze cross on Sedgwick’s gravestone, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Program for the dedication of the Sedgwick Monument, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Article on Sedgwick Monument in The Chimes, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence of C.L. Gold, regarding Sedgwick Monument, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence of Theodore Sedgwick Gold. regarding Sedgwick Monument, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper accounts of Sedgwick Monument dedication, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    - Letter sent to J. Sedgwick Cooke from The American Red Cross, regarding 50th anniversary of the Sedgwick Monument, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Documents from Centennial Committee of Sedgwick’s death, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
    - Documents from the rededication of the Sedgwick Monument, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous Materials
  - Documents related to Sedgwick’s ceremonial sword, 1864-1878; , undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Documents related to Sedgwick statue at West Point, 1864-1909 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Text of memorial address given at Vermont Officer’s Reunion Society, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings about Gen. John Sedgwick, 1885-1910; , undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Books and other publication about Gen. John Sedgwick, 1905-1966; , undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings related to books about Gen. John Sedgwick, 1900-1903 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - List of letters received for Life of Gen. Sedgwick, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings related to Sedgwick statue at Gettysburg, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Items related to Sedgwick memorial in Vermont, 1937-1954 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence related to Sedgwick statue at Gettysburg, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Items related to Cornwall Historical Society’s acquisition of Sedgwick documents, 1893-1954 (Box 6, Folder 12)